<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter out of the country to a member of this present Parliament occasioned by a late letter to a member of the House of Commons, concerning the bishops lately in the Tower and now under suspension.</title>
            <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50337</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34531</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14507337</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14507337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50337)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1064:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter out of the country to a member of this present Parliament occasioned by a late letter to a member of the House of Commons, concerning the bishops lately in the Tower and now under suspension.</title>
                  <author>Maurice, Henry, 1648-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Awnsham Churchill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Maurice.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops.</term>
               <term>Nonjurors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102430:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER Out of the COUNTRY, To a MEMBER of this preſent PARLIAMENT: OCCASIONED By a late LETTER to a Member of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> Concerning the BISHOPS lately in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and now under SUSPENSION.</p>
            <p>Licenſed <hi>Nov.</hi> 7. 1689. <hi>J. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Awnſham Churchill</hi> at the <hi>Black Swan</hi> near <hi>Amen-Corner,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:102430:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102430:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> to a Member of the Houſe of Commons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE concern, which in your laſt to me you were pleas'd to expreſs for thoſe good Biſhops now under Suſpenſion for not taking the Oaths, and your earneſt Enquiry after ſome Expedient to prevent their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Deſtitution, do well become that Character of Goodneſs and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, by which you are known no leſs than by your Name. It is ſome comfort to ſee, that a Perſon of your Underſtanding and Practice in the World, doth not yet deſpair, nor give up theſe Excellent but Unfortunate Perſons as loſt beyond poſſibility of recovery. Some begin to bewail their Fall already, as a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable, and others may be caſting lots for the Garments; there is nothing that the Church of <hi>England</hi> in general deſires more than the Preſervation of theſe bright and ſhining Lights, that direct and adorn her; and cannot think with any patience that they ſhould be extinguiſhed in Diſhonour. They have the Compaſſion and the good Wiſhes of the People; which if they have not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Effect, yet may ſerve for a good Omen, and portend ſomething better than what now appears. But after all, there can be no ground of Hopes but by a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for the Act has left no other Remedy, and we cannot expect that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power ſhould now revive to ſave thoſe from whom it received its mortal Wound in the laſt Reign: Now Providence has ſo far favour'd their Cauſe, that a Parliament is aſſembled within the Time aſſign'd for taking the Oaths, and before the laſt Severities are to fall upon the Refuſers; and who can tell but it may be with a Deſign to give that great Aſſembly an opportunity to find ſome Relief for theſe Reverend Biſhops, who have deſerv'd ſo well of this Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and whoſe abſolute Ruine cannot but be diſhonourable and invidious.</p>
            <p>I do not pretend to juſtifie their Refuſal of taking the Oaths; but wiſh with all my heart they would yet take them, and bring their Conſcience to go along with the Stream of the Publick Judgment: that they would conſider what allowance is to be made for the real Neceſſities of a Kingdom, and whether the Safety of a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple muſt not be preferr'd to all ordinary humane Rule. We of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have the greateſt reaſon in the World to wiſh this; for we cannot but account it one of the greateſt Calamities that can befall us, to ſee the chiefeſt and beſt of our Guides divided from the major part and general Conſent of the Nation. But our Affliction will be inſupportable, if we muſt ſee our ſelves deprived of ſuch Men, under whoſe Conduct we have found Safety and Honour in the moſt difficult Times; and ſee them, whom we reverence and love as Fathers, diſgrac'd, and depos'd, and undone, becauſe they boggle in a kind of moot Point of Conſcience, and cannot ſatisfie their Minds about the Oaths now enjoyn'd.</p>
            <p>Nor can I much wonder that ſeveral of the Clergy have their Scruples upon this occaſion; for Men of Retirement and Study are not ſo quick in a Change, as Stateſmen, and thoſe who have the Experience and Practice of the World. As thoſe who keep within doors, are not ſo ſoon ſenſible of alteration of Weather, as thoſe who are abroad and live in the open Air. Beſides, the Arguments for the maintenance of our rightful Liberties and juſt Defence, and all the grounds of our Common and Neceſſary preſervation have been ſo miſerably abus'd, by reſtleſs and ſeditious Men, that they have loſt a great deal of their Operation. They have been ſo often pretended without reaſon, that when the real Caſe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102430:3"/>Neceſſity happens, many may be apt to ſuſpect it for Counterfeit and meer Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; as thoſe who have been too often abus'd with falſe Alarms, may not ſo readily be brought to arm and prepare upon a real one.</p>
            <p>The Parliament therefore, that made this Actt enjoyning theſe Oaths, could not but foreſee that ſeveral of the Clergy might probably be under great difficulties upon this Occaſion; and upon this Proſpect thought fit to exempt Twelve Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from ſome part of the Penalties of the Statute, ſo far as to leave them at the King's Diſcretion for a third Part of their Revenues; which ſhews that in the Opinion of this very Parliament there might be ſome Refuſers not unworthy of Favour. But it is poſſible they might not foreſee al that happen'd, nor think that the Rigour and Severity of that Act ſhould in a manner wholly fall upon ſuch Perſons, who are the Chief for Merits as well as Authority in our Church, and that they only ſhould feel the Extremities of that Law, who had deſerv'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother kind of acknowledgment and return from the Nation, for that unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell'd Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, and for the Priviledges and Liberty of the Subject, which in ſo ſignal a manner they ſhew'd in the laſt Reign.</p>
            <p>It is little more than a year, ſince moſt of the Biſhops, who are now ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate as not to be able to reconcile their Conſciences to the Oaths, were hurried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Priſon for their oppoſition to Popery and Slavery. The Zeal and Courage which they made appear upon that occaſion, cannot ſo ſoon be forgot; for who cannot but have yet a lively remembrance, how ſenſible the whole Nation was affected with their Sufferings and Enlargements? how all ſorts of People were concern'd, as if the Fate of the Kingdom had been ty'd to theirs, and all muſt have been ruin'd or preſerv'd with them: I might mention the Malice and Virulence of their Proſecution, and how near Treaſon it was then thought by ſome to oppoſe King <hi>James</hi> his Arbitrary Power. But I do not now call the Sufferings of theſe great Men in remembrance with any deſign to render the Inſtruments of them odious: But to let you ſee how ſtrange a thing it will appear to the preſent Age and to Poſterity, that thoſe Prelates who had eſcap'd the fury of Papiſts, and had made ſo glorious a Confeſſion for Proteſtant Religion and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, ſhould in ſo little a compaſs of time come to be diſgrac'd and depos'd, and ruin'd under a Proteſtant Government, without any high Crime laid to their Charge, but only becauſe they cannot prevail with their Conſciences to take the Oaths; which tho' I think to be juſt and neceſſary, yet cannot but acknowledge to have ſome Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances that are unuſual and extraordinary.</p>
            <p>It might be expected upon the Deliverance of this Nation from Popery and Tyranny, that thoſe who had ſtood in the gap, and diſtinguiſh'd themſelves by the check and ſtop which they gave to the Progreſs of thoſe ſpreading plagues, might have been proportionably diſtinguiſh'd by the Countenance and Favour of the next Settlement; but the Ruine of ſuch men under this Government will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unaccountable, when we conſider what Lenity it has us'd to all ſorts of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders; when we ſee few or none of all thoſe Perfidious Wretches, who joyn'd in the Attempt of enſlaving and undoing this Nation, ſo much as call'd in queſtion; when the Proſecutors of the Biſhops are not only receiv'd into mercy, but into favour. What can People think, What can they ſay, when they ſee the chief Champions for Proteſtant Religion and Liberty to be the only Men that are ruin'd by the Change? What will foreign Nations think of us, ſince even among them the Names of theſe Biſhops are become venerable? for their Reputation has reach'd as far as Proteſtant Religion does extend. Thoſe who have applauded
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102430:3"/>them from far, and acknowledg'd them as the chiefeſt and braveſt Defenders of the common Cauſe; what will they think, when they come to hear, that after the deliverance of the Kingdom, thoſe whom they admir'd at ſuch a diſtance, are cover'd with diſhonour, and depriv'd of every thing, but the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Conſcience of their Merits? There will be but poor Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for any hereafter to hazard themſelves for the Publick good, while they have before their Eyes ſuch ſad and frightful Recompenſes as this.</p>
            <p>Nay, tho' there had been no proviſion at all made for any other ſcrupulous perſon in this caſe, yet the ſignal merit of theſe Biſhops might leave room for a Special Plea in their behalf. But when <hi>Quakers</hi> are thought not unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of particular proviſion and tenderneſs; a Sect who are known to this Kingdom by no good Office or uſefulneſs; but are fallen under the juſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and deteſtation of the Kingdom for their conjunction with King <hi>James;</hi> when theſe come to be humour'd in their Nonſence, excus'd from Oaths, exempted from the Penalties of this Act, while this ſtands in the very Body of our Law, and is allowed throughout the whole Kingdom: how can any one, without indignation ſee the chief Biſhops of our Church, and the celebrated Patriots of our Liberties, fall an unbecoming and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sacrifice to this Act, and endure its laſt Extremities, from which ſuch humorſom and ſullen Impoſtors are exempted?</p>
            <p>Now theſe Biſhops Character and manner of Life diſpoſe them to peace; their proper buſineſs, which is not of this World, is not likely to give them leave to be overbuſie in troubling the Affairs of it; their Zeal for the Proteſtant Religion, which is beyond diſpute; their Love of their Country and the Laws, which appear'd ſufficiently to the whole Kingdom: theſe things, in my judgment, tho' they do not take the Oaths, are much a better and more ſolid ſecurity than any <hi>Quakers</hi> Declaration can amount to.</p>
            <p>Now as I cannot but think it reaſonable, that theſe worthy Biſhops ſhould have ſome relief in their preſent diſtreſs, before it be too late; ſo I am of opinion, this may be more proper time to do it, than when the Act was in making. For then there might be good reaſon to make ſome ſhew of rigour; for the Government was but new, and requir'd, that all ſorts of Men ſhould declare Allegiance to it; but now the Act having operated ſufficiently, and the generality of the Clergy having taken the Oaths, the Examples of theſe Biſhops can have no ill influence, and the favour that ſhall be ſhewed them will be only Perſonal, and draw no conſequence of danger after it; for the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Church is ſufficiently ſecur'd, ſince none can receive either Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or Preferment, without taking the Oaths.</p>
            <p>And as it can be no prejudice to the Government, to preſerve theſe good Men: ſo I am ſure it will be very honourable, and give it credit both at home and abroad. You know as well as I, that there cannot be any thing more acceptable to the generality of the Kingdom. You can ſearce meet with any man, that will not wiſh it were in his power to reſtore them. I have ſpoken with ſeveral of your Houſe, and with ſome of the Lords, and I find all well-wiſhers: What then can hinder the effect of ſo univerſal an Inclination? I have not the honour to be of your Houſe at this time; it was indifferent to me whether it ſhould be you or I; nay, <hi>I</hi> am better ſatisfi'd, that you are there, ſince I know you wiſh as well as <hi>I</hi> can to this matter, and have greater dexterity and credit in the Houſe to bring
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102430:4"/>it to paſs. They are much miſtaken, who fancy that the ſuſpended Biſhops have by their refuſal of the Oaths forfeited all that credit which they got with the People in King <hi>James</hi> his time; for, as far as I can obſerve, the People are rather ſorry, than angry with them for not complying; and when they are once depos'd, will be much more ſenſible, of their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which is viſible, than of the reaſon of it, which will not be ſo eaſily comprehended. And even the Clergy who have taken the Oaths, are ſo far from diminiſhing the Affection and Reverence they had for their Biſhops, that they rather increaſe from the conſideration of their misfortune. The Clergy look upon the Deprivation, which without relief from this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt ſhortly fall upon their Biſhops, to be more a puniſhment to the Dioceſes, than the Dioceſans. In proper ſpeaking, they are rather depriv'd of their Biſhops, than the Biſhops of their Preferments; and I dare ſay, it there were any appearance of hope, the reſpective Dioceſes would quickly petition for the Reſtauration of their Governours, and beſeech you in the moſt render and paſſionate manner in the World, that you would not leave them Orphans while their Fathers are alive; and they are like to continue ſo while theſe Biſhops are living, ſince it can ſcarce be conceiv'd, that any worthy Men will be forward to accept theſe Preferments, and thereby ſhut the door againſt their Predeceſſors, ſo as to make their return impoſſible. For notwithſtanding Deprivation, as long as the Places are void, the depriv'd Biſhops are in a poſſibility of being reſtor'd; but when the Seats are one fill'd, there can be no remedy; ſo that the Succeſſors, and not the Law, will be look'd upon as the Deprivers: And if the Ambition of any ſhould be ſo prevalent, as to deſpiſe the invidiouſneſs of ſuch Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; they muſt conſider, that they will have but little authority over their Clergy or People, and can do but little good, where they are judg'd to intrude to the prejudice of the old Poſſeſſors, for whom both Clergy and People have ſo great eſteem; and tho' they may have legal right and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and be Biſhops and Fathers in Law, yet as long as their Predeceſſors are in being, and in poſſeſſion of the hearts of their People, and look'd upon as depriv'd not for any Canonical Reaſons, but for their Misfortune rather than their Fault; the New-comers can expect to be but ſorrily belov'd, and will have great difficulty to maintain the Peace and Unity of their Church. Beſides, the Reverſion of the Biſhopricks to be voided upon this occaſion doth not ſeem to me to be very deſirable upon another account, even tho' they ſhould become vacant in an ordinary way; for thoſe who ſucceed them will find it a hard task to come up to the pitch of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors merit and reputation, and will probably be leſſen'd by compariſon with thoſe that are forc'd to quit; but when men will enter upon the ruine of thoſe to whom they are found ſo inferior, their reception is like to be but very indifferent.</p>
            <p>Since therefore it is not an impoſſible thing, while the Parliament ſits, to reſtore the Biſhops now under ſuſpenſion, and it can be no prejudice to the Government, ſince it is ſo generally wiſh'd, ſo honourable, and at the ſame time ſo ſafe, ſince their final deprivation may bring great Inconveniences, and not the leaſt advantage to the Publick, It is to be hop'd, that the Wiſdom of this Parliament will find out ſome Expedient to reſtore them to the Exerciſe of their Office, and the Church to the Benefit of their Adminiſtration.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102430:4"/>
            <head>A LETTER Out of the COUNTRY, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce you ſeem to deſire my thoughts of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you ſent me, altho I am at preſent pretty much indiſpoſed, yet I had much rather give my ſelf a little uneaſineſs than fruſtrate your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation, not queſtioning but your Friendſhip can make allowances for the miſtakes, and little pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhneſſes too, to which Sickeſs may ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray one; for I muſt confeſs if I had not thought my ſelf pretty much maſter of my own Notions as to this point, I ſhould not have attempted giving you an account of them at this time.</p>
            <p>As to the Letter then about the Biſhops, I cannot but ſay, That as to the main Deſign (at leaſt as it appears to me,) I muſt approve of it, as I'm ſure you will ſay, I ſhall of any thing that ſounds in favour of thoſe excellent Perſons, for whom I have ſo particular a veneration, that you your ſelf can witneſs I have often wiſht there might be ſome Expedient found out to keep them from ſuffering the rigour of that Law, to which they ſo wilfully expoſe themſelves. And altho I ſtill continue in the ſame Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet I cannot ſay I approve of the Methods propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102430:5"/>for I doubt he has begun at the wrong end: For in my apprehenſion, he ſhould in the firſt place have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed himſelf to the Biſhops, and perſuaded them to have deſired before he had ſo peremptorily preſcribed the giving a Diſpenſation to the Parliament. But alas! I know how very hard it is, not to be partial where one has particular affection; it having been a failing to which I have been too much inclined my ſelf, even in the ſame caſe. But having taken ſome pains to place things in the true Light, perhaps it may be a piece of Service to ſhew them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in it. And to that purpoſe I ſhall crave leave to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the two differing Matters of Fact, that of refuſing the Declaration from King <hi>James,</hi> and the Oath to King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> As to the proof of both, I think there needs not much evidence, ſince the whole Nation is their Teſtimonial in that Point: And for the Inferences that may be made by either ſide. I deſire to ſet them apart for the preſent, and to conſider the Actions in their naked circumſtances. And in the firſt place, Here is an ill thing impos'd on them by King <hi>James,</hi> and not only ſo, but they are required to be Parties in it, and ſpread it all over the Nation. And now I would only ask this Queſtion. Whether it was their Duty to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe this Command or no? If not, they ſinn'd (I'm ſure, according to their own Doctrine) in diſobeying King <hi>James;</hi> but if it was their Duty to refuſe (as I ſuppoſe we all grant,) then we may gather up this obſervation by the by, That the Commands of Kings may, nay ought to be reſiſted, if in themſelves unlawful, that is, againſt the Law of the Land, (for that is their main Objection to the Declaration.) But altho they had been very faulty if they had comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet, without admitting the Popiſh Doctrine of Superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Merit, I cannot ſee why they ſhould boaſt, or we magnify them ſo extreamly for doing that which was their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102430:5"/>indiſpenſable Duty; nay, I'm confident thoſe excellent Perſons have too much Humility to do it, or elſe they had not learn'd our Saviour's Leſſon ſo well as I believe they have, who in the 17th of St. <hi>Luke, verſ.</hi> the 9th. asks, if a Maſter <hi>doth thank a Servant for doing thoſe things that were commanded him?</hi> And anſwers, <hi>I trow not.</hi> To which he preſently ſubjoins in the 10th. verſe, <hi>So likewiſe ye, when ye ſhall have done all that is commanded, ſay we are unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servants, we have done that which was our Duty to do.</hi> But altho nothing can hold weight in the Balance of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and no Fleſh muſt glory in the preſence of God; yet <hi>Elihu</hi> has well obſerved, <hi>Job</hi> 35.8. <hi>Thy Righteouſneſs may profit a Son of Man.</hi> And on that account it muſt be owned, that there never was Action by which a whole Nation was more obliged than by that of the Biſhops. But yet we ſhould be too partial to them; and unjuſt to others, ſhould we ſuffer them to engroſs all the Praiſe of that great and glorious Scene; the remembrance of which puts me almoſt into an extaſie. For was there ever any ſight ſo tranſporting, as that to ſee the Church aſſerting, the Law defending, the Nobility aſſiſting, and all agreeing in the defence of our true and ancient Liberties, and that to the face, and in defiance of Arbitrary and Diſpenſing Power. For how gallantly ſoever the Biſhops behaved themſelves in that undertaking, had not ſome of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Clergy been as forward as themſelves; and had they not been as bravely ſeconded by the Lords, and Lawyers too, neither their Courage nor Innocency had been of any uſe either to themſelves or us: So that to be juſt, we muſt divide the Praiſe and Thanks due to that great Action; which I am very unwilling to leave, becauſe, alas! I muſt now divert to a leſs pleaſing Subject, Their refuſing of the Oaths. And how many Partners ſoever they had in their applauded part, I find they muſt bear the blame of this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102430:6"/>for no body pretends to ſhare with them in that; ſo that they muſt either ſtand or fall by themſelves. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſhall be ſo kind to them, as to make them Judges in their own Cauſes; for to go through the whole Diſpute would be much too long for a Letter: But I only deſire the diſſenting Biſhops to review, and conſider their own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of <hi>December</hi> the 10th. 1688. for ſo I think I may call it, being ſigned by ſo many of them; for <hi>W Cant.</hi> is (I am ſure) the firſt Name, and the Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> was not only one that ſign'd, but carried it to the then P. of <hi>O.</hi> And I would fain ask what their Lordſhips then thought? For if they did not then think King <hi>James</hi> had diſſerted the Government, I am very confident they would not have done what they then did. For I am ſure they take upon them as if there was no King in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And becauſe 'tis poſſible you may not have the Declaration by you, I will with your good leave tranſcribe ſome part of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We do therefore unanimouſly reſolve to apply to the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>who with ſo great kindneſs to theſe Kingdoms, ſo vaſt Expence, and ſo much hazard to his own Perſon, hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, by endeavouring to procure a Free Parliament, to reſcue us, with as little effuſion as poſſible of Chriſtian Blood, from the imminent Dangers of Popery and Slavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And we do hereby declare, That we will with our utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour aſſiſt His Highneſs in the obtaining ſuch a Parliament with all ſpeed, wherein our Laws, our Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties may be ſecured, the Church of</hi> England <hi>in particular, with a due liberty to Proteſtant Diſſenters, and in general the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt over the whole World, may be ſupported and encouraged, to the Glory of God, the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Eſtabliſht Government in theſe Kingdoms, and the advantage of all Princes and States in Chriſtendom that may be herein concerned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102430:6"/>
               <hi>And in the mean time we will endeavour to preſerve Peace, taking care to diſarm all Papiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if there be any thing more to be performed by us, for promoting his Highneſs generous Intentions for the publick Good, we ſhall be ready to do it as occaſion ſhall require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the very words of the Declaration which was ſign'd and delivered too by the Perſons above-mentioned, ſo that we have reaſon to look upon it as their own Act and Deed: And muſt therefore beg leave to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in one Point, and that is, By what Authority their Lordſhips did this? And I cannot ſuppoſe they will ſay it was done by any Deputation from King <hi>James,</hi> or any Power they derived from him; ſo then it ſeems they did it in their own right. And if ſo, 'tis pretty indifferent to me whether King <hi>James</hi> diſſerted or no; for let them take which fide they pleaſe, either will do my buſineſs. For if they will own the Diſſertion, they yield the Point we have all this while contended for; but if they deny that, and ſay that King <hi>James</hi> was at that time actually their King, then I perceive that Subjects may preſcribe to, nay, force their Kings to do their Duty. But what becomes of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> all this while I wonder? For here we find our good Biſhops not only applauding, but joining with, and aſſiſting that very Perſon whom their King <hi>James</hi> called an Invader, and whoſe very Errand hither, as they themſelves at that time very well knew, was only to teach him better Behaviour.</p>
            <p>And how they can avoid one of theſe Conſequences (for we may allow them their choice), I muſt confeſs I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not very well ſee: For the involuntary Return which King <hi>James</hi> did make to <hi>London,</hi> does not, in my Conceit, much alter the matter, unleſs we will allow Kings to play at <hi>Boe-peep</hi> with their Government; and now they will be ſeen, and now they will not. But I hope the Perſons I was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102430:7"/>now ſpeaking of, have too much Gravity, as well as Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, to approve of, much leſs to act their Part in ſuch Boys-Play, eſpecially in things of this Nature and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. And yet, to our great wonder, as well as trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we find thoſe very wiſe Men recalling their Conſent, flying from their Subſcriptions, and nauſeating all thoſe great and glorious Deſigns they then ſeemed ſo eagerly to purſue: For ſince that very Free Parliament has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, and the Rights of this particular Church and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well as the Intereſt of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, ſecured, as far as Humane Wiſdom can reach; now they loath this <hi>Manna,</hi> and long for the <hi>Fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pots</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; and with the Men in the Goſpel, they will not have this Man (though courted before) to reign over them. Now what can one ſay to Men of this Temper? Nay, what can God himſelf do for them, ſince they are diſpleaſed with Heaven for granting their Deſires, and quarrel with Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence becauſe the Change was not made exactly by their Model, although, for any thing I perceive, they were not very well agreed about it themſelves. For ſhould we have attended till they had pleaſed themſelves with a Scheme of our Deliverance, 'tis probable we might all, before that, have been ſwallow'd up in that Common Ruine which was then juſt ready to overflow the Nation. But pardon me, dear Sir, if my Zeal for the Publick have tranſported me too far in this Point; For it would raiſe ſomething of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation in any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, that had a true ſenſe of his Countries Intereſt, to ſee People ſent abroad (God forbid I ſhould ſay, by the Biſhops; for I have a much better Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them; but however, by thoſe that pretend to be of their Party) to proclaim, That <hi>now Iniquity is Eſtabliſht by a Law.</hi> But whether what they are pleaſed to call <hi>Iniquity Eſtabliſht by a Law,</hi> is not at a venture better than a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Power, that will both Eſtabliſh and Maintain Idolatry
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102430:7"/>and Cruelty; I fancy is a Point that will be pretty eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, if left to the Majority of Voices in this Nation.</p>
            <p>But I have been hitherto relating only Matters of Fact, which I hope I have done ſo impartially, that they only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion I have made, I believe will be found to flow very Naturally from my Premiſes; that is indeed, from the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration that was both ſigned and ſent by theſe Worthy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
            <p>Now to return to the Letter you ſent me. I find the Author does not only think the Oaths Lawful, but Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary; wherein I muſt agree with him, as I do alſo in wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Biſhops would yet take them, and, as he well ſays, <hi>bring their Conſciences to go along with the Stream of the Publick Judgment: That they would conſider what allowance is to be made for the Real Neceſſities of a Kingdom; and whether the Safety of a People muſt not be preferr'd to all ordinary hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Rule.</hi> And theſe being the very Words of their own Advocate, I knew not how to put my <hi>Queries</hi> into more proper Terms; and therefore recite them: and where <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Populi eſt Suprema Lex,</hi> is the avow'd Maxim of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Conſtitution, one would think it ſhould not require much deliberation to anſwer the Queſtion. But now, if they pleaſe, we will come to diſpute the matter in cool Blood, and ſhall not reſtrain this great Law only to the Subject; but by the Safety of the People, underſtand the Government in the Concrete: For we know the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is derived from the <hi>Old Romans,</hi> among whom the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, with their Senate, did carry the Face of the Supream Magiſtracy: And we may be ſure the Safety of the whole was intended by it. So that in our Conſtitution it would be very hard to ſhut out the King from his Share in it, and ſay, he was not at all concern'd in that Maxim: But yet in admitting a Head, I would not exclude the Body. And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102430:8"/>although 'tis poſſible Kingdoms may have ſuffer'd by the Peoples Encroachments upon the Royal Prerogative, yet to ſay, That a Government can ſuffer in no other Inſtance, would be full as abſurd as to ſay, That a Man can be Mortally wounded no where but in his Head: But we are ſure there are parts in our Body as fatal to be touch'd as the Brain it ſelf; and therefore ought to be guarded with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual care: And in all well-order'd Commonwealths the Rights of the Subjects ought to be as Sacred as thoſe of the Soveraign: Or elſe we ſhould invert the very End and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of Government in its firſt Inſtitution; which certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was not erected only for the agrandiſing one ſingle Perſon or Family, but was intended for the Safety of the whole: Therefore in thoſe Caſes we are not tied up to the Rigour and Words of a Law: For if the Moral Equity, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Commandment, is better obſerv'd by breaking the Letter of it, 'tis ſurely very lawful, nay, our Duty to do it. And this holding in Divine, muſt by a ſtronger Reaſon do ſo in Humane Laws: for the Poſitive Precepts of the <hi>Decalogue</hi> it ſelf have been, and are frequently diſpenſed with, and that by God's permiſſion: As for inſtance, The great Commandment of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> although ſo eſſential a part of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law and Service, that one calls it, <hi>The very Sacrament of the Worſhip of the True God, the Creator of Heaven and Earth, in oppoſition to Idolatry.</hi> Whether it deſerves that Title, or no, I know not; yet I think I may very properly ſtile it, <hi>The Diſtinguiſhing Character of the Jewiſh Church;</hi> and that it is a Precept which is the ofteſt repeated, more Promiſes made to the Obſervers of it, and more Judgments threaten'd to the Breakers of it, than to all the other Commands of the Law: So that I ſhould make this ſwell to a Volume, ſhould I tranſcribe all the Texts wherein the Obſervation of the Sabbath is enjoyn'd. And yet, for all that God ſeems to lay ſo particular a ſtreſs on
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102430:8"/>that Commandment, you ſee our Saviour blames the <hi>Jews</hi> for adhering ſo ſtrictly to the Letter of it, for the ſaving of the Life of an Ox or Aſs, was to be preferr'd before their Obedience to it. But waving all thoſe Inſtances which our Saviour gives us in the Goſpel, wherein the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves did break the Sabbath, and were blameleſs: I ſhall inſiſt only on one Story in the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> which is pretty much to this purpoſe, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 2. beginning at the 31. Verſe, where we have the Relation of the Fate of thoſe poor miſtaken <hi>Jews,</hi> who, for fear of prophaning the Sabbath, would not ſo much as ſtop the Paſſages againſt their Enemies, but let them come in, and kill them tamely, without ſtriking a ſtroke. But <hi>Mattathias</hi> and his Sons, though as great Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots for the Law as any we read of, yet ſeemed to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that Point better; and in <hi>ver.</hi> 41. 'tis ſaid, <hi>At that time therefore they decreed, ſaying, Whoſoever ſhall come to make battle with us on the Sabbath day, we will fight againſt him; neither will we die all, as our brethren that were mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the ſecret places;</hi> which was ſurely a lawful, as well as prudent Reſolution. And truly juſt ſuch wiſe <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> ſhould we have been to the Fifth Commandment, as they were to the Fourth, had we purſued the Notion of <hi>Paſſive Obedience</hi> ſo far as ſome would have had us; by which we ſhould have betray'd both our Religion and our Friends, and at once have render'd our ſelves the Prey and Scorn of our Enemies: For we are not to think that God Almighty will work Miracles for the maintaining of our fanciful Opinions and Comments on his Law: For if we will lay Neceſſities on our ſelves, and chuſe Deſtruction when he allows means of Eſcape, it is but reaſonable we ſhould periſh: For that, generally ſpeaking, is his method, as to this World, as well as to the next. We muſt do our part to ſave our ſelves, or he will never help us; There muſt be the Sword of <hi>Gideon,</hi> as well as the Sword of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102430:9"/>Lord, if we deſign to get the Victory: for we ſee that God ſuffer'd the <hi>Paſſive Jews</hi> to periſh, but bleſt the <hi>Active Maccabees</hi> with moſt miraculous Victories, while in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Law they broke the Commandment. And a great many more Arguments might be drawn from the ſame Topick, but that I fear to ſwell this to too large a bulk: Therefore to conclude this Point, I ſhall only recite what our Saviour ſaith of the Fourth Commandment, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27. <hi>The Sabbath was made for Man, not Man for the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath:</hi> Which may as properly be apply'd to the Fifth: for we may as truly ſay, Kings were made for the People, not the People for Kings.</p>
            <p>But I doubt you will think that I forget my Letter all this while; but I was ſo taken up with his Wiſh, That the Biſhops would take the Oath, that I could not but ſay all I could to induce them to it: But alas! ſo many have fail'd in that Attempt, that I dare hardly hope my weak Arguments ſhould be more powerful. But now to my apprehenſion this is downright Demonſtration, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is lawful to obey K. <hi>W.</hi> or 'tis not; if 'tis law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, why then may not any Man ſwear they will do ſo? For certainly, any body may lawfully ſwear to do a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing, eſpecially when the Law requires them to do it. But indeed, if they do not think it lawful to obey King <hi>William,</hi> then they have no reaſon to take the Oath, nor truly has the Author very much to expect that the King or Parliament ſhould grant Diſpenſations to them that avow'dly diſown their Authority, and diſobey their Laws. But perhaps it will be urged, that this is not the Law; but I'm ſure our Saviour tells us, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.23. <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me:</hi> And 'tis ſo hard a thing to be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Neuter, that all ſides ſuſpect them that pretend to be ſo: Therefore it would give great ſatisfaction, if theſe Worthy Perſons would declare themſelves. And beſides,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102430:9"/>it is ſo reaſonable a thing to give Security to that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from which they receive Protection, that no Sect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes doing it after ſome way or other: And if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops do really ſtumble at the Oath, yet 'tis poſſible for them to contrive ſome other way of binding themſelves as firm, and giving as good ſecurity to the Government, as if they had taken that. But 'tis their part to propoſe it, for they are not to expect that the Parliament ſhould be proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting ways to evade their own Laws, or offer Relief to thoſe Grievances that were never complain'd of to them: The Biſhops know the way, and alſo know their Right of Petitioning; which makes ſome people ſuſpect, that they had not ſo much to ſay for their refuſing the Oaths, as they had for the Declaration; or elſe they would not have been ſo wanting to themſelves, as not to have done it before now, unleſs the neglect proceed from a worſe Principle, that of the ſlighting and deſpiſing the Government it ſelf. And they cannot more effectually clear themſelves from that Imputation, than by propoſing ſomething that may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent to the Oath, and conſequently as good Security to the Government: Which if refuſed, they will then have ſomething to ſay for themſelves, and may lawfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. But I believe, Sir, that you have reaſon to think it would be accepted if offer'd; and at a venture I dare pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them your Vote; for the Author of this Letter is not the only one that has wiſh'd ſome Expedient might be found out, that thoſe excellent Perſons might continue in the Station they ſo well became.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Letter is only Panegyrick of the Biſhops, and a Prophecy of the Reſentment that the whole Nation is to expreſs when the Sentence comes to Deprivation: And as to the <hi>Encomium</hi> he makes of them, I ſhould be very well pleaſed with it in the <hi>Poſitive</hi> Degree; but <hi>Compariſons,</hi> they ſay, are odious: But why they ſhould be advanced to the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102430:10"/>
               <hi>Superlative,</hi> only for not taking the Oaths, I do not ſo well underſtand; for we have Two of the famous Seven, who may pretend to as great Merit as any, for I am ſure they ſuffered as much as the other Five needed to have done; and I think do not deſerve the leſs from the Nation, becauſe they have not made a Faction and Schiſm in it, as the others have, nor been the occaſion of the expence of ſo much Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Blood too. For whatever obligation we in <hi>England</hi> may have to them, I doubt the poor <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtants have not ſo; for I believe you, and a great many in your Houſe, are ſatisfied, That if the Church of <hi>England</hi> had unanimouſly come in to King <hi>William</hi> at firſt, ſo that he could have ſent his Army over while the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland</hi> had been in a condition to have aſſiſted them, that Kingdom had been reduced long ago; and conſequently ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lives ſaved as it has, and will coſt to do it now.</p>
            <p>But this is not a Subject for <hi>me</hi> to inſiſt on, tho it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves <hi>their</hi> conſideration: But I perceive the Author thinks there is no falling from Grace; elſe he would not have concluded that after one Eminent good Act, it was impoſſible for them to do an ill. It would indeed be very happy if one generous piece of Piety would render one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ever after; but I fear the rule will fail, though I heartily wiſh it may not in thoſe Reverend Perſons, for whom I have as great and true a Veneration as any body can pretend to. But in caſe they ſhould think fit to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Quiet and Privacy, before Profit and State; and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to their own humour, before ſerving God and the Church in the places they ſo well fill'd; if I ſay they ſhould think fit to do this, I cannot ſuppoſe thoſe diſmal conſequences muſt neceſſarily follow that this Author fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels: for I fear the generality of the People do not ſo much value true worth, as to be concerned for what good Men ſuffer, if they themſelves are at eaſe, and in ſafety.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102430:10"/>But good words coſt nothing, and they can eaſily afford them, that will not do any thing more to ſerve either King or Biſhop: Which may be one reaſon why both have been ſo out in their computation. For King <hi>James</hi> making his Muſters by his Addreſſes, I'm ſure reckon'd without his Hoſt: and I fancy the Biſhops have been a little out in their Count too, as to the numbers of the Clergy that would refuſe the Oaths; as 'tis poſſible this Author may be in his. But indeed where the diſſenting Biſhops are the whole Church, a very ſmall Party may by the ſame reaſon be the whole Nation; and both contained in a good honeſt Conventicle. Nay, for any thing I know, at the rate ſome men talk, both Church and Nation may in a few years be reduced, as the Church of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> was, to one ſingle Perſon. But I do not deſire to be a Prophet in that point, for I do from my Soul wiſh that we may be all united as in one Faith, ſo in one Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; that we may with one Heart, and one Mouth Praiſe God, and Pray for our King, whom God has been pleaſed to make the Glorious Inſtrument of the greateſt Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance that ever yet happened to the Reformed Church. And truly it does ſeem as ſtrange to me, that any body that calls himſelf a Church of <hi>England</hi> Man doth not both ſee and acknowledge that, as it does to this Author to think that the great Aſſertors of the Proteſtant Religion and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties ſhould be Suſpended, and Deprived. But the latter is ſtill in their own choice, and let them but qualify themſelves for Their Majeſties Favour, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the Law, and I do not queſtion but they ſhall receive ſuch marks of it, as ſhall be proportionable even to their Merits. Which I do think as great as any body can pretend to, but without admitting the Doctrine of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, I cannot ſay that the Sepererogating in one point of the Law ſhould give one Licenſe to break another: For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102430:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.10. That <hi>whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law, and yet offend in one point, is guilty of all.</hi> And I ſuppoſe this holds in Humane as well as in the Divine Law. Therefore unleſs they do think fit to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, I cannot help it though the Law do look upon them as Criminals, though I muſt always admire their Perſonal Endowments, and particular qualifications for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which makes it ſo deſirable they ſhould keep their Stations. But if they think fit to deprive the Church of their further Service, (for after all the exclamation that is, or can be made againſt it, 'tis apparently their own doings, becauſe their choice) although the Proverb, <hi>That ſeldom comes a letter,</hi> may be very likely to hold in their Caſe, yet I do not think there is ſo great a ſcarcity of Worthy Men in the Church, but that it may be poſſible to find out four or five as good, who may be able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, even their places, and come up to their pitch. Of which the two laſt Vacancies is a convincing inſtance to me; for by that time that the Dioceſſes of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter</hi> are thoroughly acquainted with their New Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, I do not believe they will think they have chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged much for the worſe; although the two Predeceſſors were as Eminent, and as good men, as any they have left behind them.</p>
            <p>But I fear I have exceeded the bounds of a Letter, tho' I hope not thoſe of your Patience, for I queſtion not but you can pardon a Fault to which I was betray'd by my obedience to your Commands; for all your deſires you know are ſo to,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate Friend, and Servant.</signed>
               <date>Nov. 1. 89.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
